Finding Aid for George G. Cameron papers, 1952-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George G. Cameron papers 1952-1978
Cameron, George Glenn, 1905-
1 linear foot
85106 Aa 2
Professor of Near Eastern Languages and Literature at the University of Michigan; personal and professional correspondence relating to archeological expeditions and discoveries in Iran and the Near East.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. George Cameron (donor no. 2688 ) and came to the library in 1982.
The collection is open to research.
George G. Cameron was born July 30, 1905 in Washington, Pa. He studied at Washington and Jefferson College and then received a bachelor's degree from Muskingum College in 1927. He earned a master's degree (1930) and a Ph. D (1932) both from the University of Chicago's Oriental Institute. He taught Assyro-Babylonian cuneiform and related studies at Chicago until 1948, when he came to the University of Michigan as professor and founder of the Department of Near Eastern Studies. He was chairman of the department from 1948 to 1969. He continued to teach until 1975.
As a scholar, Cameron participated in many expeditions and explorations in the Near East. He was the author of many books, articles, and reviews, as well as the editor of texts of Assyro-Babylonian cuneiform and in Elamite and Old Persian. He was editor of the Journal of Near Eastern Studies from 1941 to 1948 and had also been editor of the American Journal of Semitic Languages and Literatures.
George Cameron died September 15, 1979.
The George Cameron papers consist of personal and professional correspondence mainly in the 1960s and 1970s. Very little of the materials relates to his work as founder and professor of the U-M Department of Near Eastern Studies. The bulk relates to his interaction and communication with other scholars in the field. The collection has been arranged into three series: Biographical, Correspondence, and Other materials.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Azazels (University of Michigan); Cameron, George Glenn, 1905-; University of Michigan. Research Club.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Near Eastern Studies.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Voyages and travels.; Travelers.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cameron, George Glenn, 1905-; Cameron family.; Iran.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - Professional
    - A-C (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Adams, Robert M. (University of Chicago), 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Alten, Ivan, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Balcer, Jack (Ohio State University), 1970-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - D-G (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Diakonoff, Igor M (Institut Vostokovedenija, Leningrad), 1963-1975 (Box 1)
    - Gershevitch, Ilya (Cambridge), 1952-1972 (Box 1)
    - H-I (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Hallo-Kelsey-Finkelstein, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - Hallock, Richard T. (University of Chicago), 1954-1976 (Box 1)
    - Hinz, Walther (Seminar fUr Iranistik der Universitfit Gottingen, DBR), 1962-1976 (Box 1)
    - J-N (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - McAlpin, David W. (University of Pennsylvania), 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - P-R (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Parkhideh, Abbas (Tehran, Iran), 1957-1975 (Box 1)
    - Reiner, Erica (University of Chicago), 1961-1967 (Box 1)
    - S-T (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Schmidt, Hans Peter (Royal University of Leiden), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Schmitt, Rildiger (Universitit des Saarlanders, Saarbrucken, DBR), 1971-1976 (Box 1)
    - Sollberger, Edmund (British Museum), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Stolper, Matthew (University of Michigan), 1974-1978 (Box 1)
    - Stronach, David (the British Institute of Persian Studies), 1963-1976 (Box 1)
    - U-Z (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - Von Voightlander, Elizabeth, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Field Notes, 1954-1955 England and Egypt; 1964-1965 Israel; and 1974 Iran, 2 books (Box 1)
  - Organizations
    - Azazels, University of Michigan, 1970-1978 (Box 1)
    - The Research Club of the University of Michigan, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, unpublished, War Record and Atlas, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Medallions (2) given to Professor Cameron by the Iranian Government
    - The Order of Homayoun, 1949
    - The University of Tehran Honoris Causa, 1954